soft engineering radio episode 129 F
sharp would look hot one
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website possible
[Music]
welcome to another episode of the hoops
lab podcast this is Marcus on the phones
here or on the mic and today we were
talking to Luke Hoban from Microsoft and
he's the f-sharp program manager hi Luke
hi
so please introduce yourself briefly to
our listeners sure thing so my name is
Luke Obon and the program manager on
f-sharp at Microsoft an f-sharp has been
a a research project in Microsoft for
the last four or five years and just
recently last year we decided to turn it
into a supported Microsoft product and
so I am working in the group in in
Microsoft is working on taking f-sharp
from a research project and making it
supported part of the programming
languages on dotnet many people might
have heard about F sharp already and and
the sharp makes it a typical dotnet
language I guess but can you maybe give
our listeners a brief introduction of
whatever our base like you know and
sharpen a sentence or something sure F
sharp is a functional programming
language for the.net platform so that
the functional language just like many
others you know scheme list haskell ml
and it most directly inherits from the
ml family of languages and specifically
shares a core language with Oh camel but
it's a language that's really fully
integrated into net and so it takes net
strong a lo system and then bakes that
very strongly into the f-sharp language
itself and also has good tools for doing
imperative programming and for doing
sort of explorative programming in
specific domain and I guess we'll look
at some of those let's say buzzwords or
core concepts in more detail as part of
the interview so if you say it's a
functional language then I mean we've
had episodes on functional languages
before so people probably know that that
functions are are a core well aspect of
functional languages so can you maybe
elaborate a little bit on on how
functions are used and how their use is
different from what we know as functions
no Pascal horsey sure yeah so you know
in the end of the day functions are you
know in Pascal or C or sort of very
similar ideas but been in a functional
language we tend to take that a step
further and allow functions to be used
as first-class values and so they can be
passed around they can be assigned to
variables they can be put inside data
structures and make me passed as as
arguments to other functions and this
ability to pass around functions as
arguments to other functions allows you
to write sort of allows you to abstract
out pieces of code in a lot of ways that
weren't previously possible with just
standard procedural programming
techniques so functional languages tend
to really emphasize the use of that
technique so that's the that's also one
other another of your points is the
succinctness of being able to express
algorithms in a very brief succinct
fashion I guess the functional aspect of
functions are a big part of that yeah I
think the ability to pull out the common
pieces of your code and abstractor is
using using things like first-class
functions and the fact that these
languages tend to be immutable so it's
easier to pull out pieces of code makes
it so that we can ultimately write the
core of your code in a very very
succinct way that captures the sort of
domain that you're working in and so I
think that's really one of the things
you see there's a striking difference
between code typical code written in a
functional language as opposed to a
procedural or imperative style you
already mentioned the word immutable can
you I mean explain why this is important
in functional languages I guess people
know what it means you can't change a
data structure you can't mute it
migrated change it once it's definitely
find through a constructor or something
but but why is that important to
functional languages sure so I mean it's
important for functional languages for a
number of different reasons I mean the
basic idea is that you obviously as you
said you can't once you sort of a
science and some data to a variable you
can't change what that variable means
later on right and the that's beneficial
for this idea of being able to pull out
pieces of code
and reused them if you have if you can
change the values of things then you can
end up with shared state where different
parts of your system all know about the
same state and if they change it that
can affects the behavior of some other
remote component and object-oriented
techniques try to use encapsulation and
things like that to to hide away that
state and in control access to it but
when you have an immutable system it
means that you you don't have to worry
about other people trying to change your
behavior you really are entirely in
control of it but I think that becomes
really interesting just beyond the
basics of the software engineering
things it becomes interesting with the
move towards parallel and distributed
computing being more and more common
right and the fact that with the many
core era that's about to begin we really
you know parallelism and massive scale
parallelism is going to be have to be a
part of how development is done and when
you're doing parallelism really one of
the big problems that you run into one
of the big things that causes that to be
a very hard problem to solve typically
is whenever you have shared state if the
different threads that are running for
different pieces that are trying to run
independently we're all trying to talk
to that same shared State you're just
bound to run into problems and it's
really the place where watch and lots of
techniques have been come up with to try
to address that but ultimately the best
way to address it is just to avoid
having that shared state in functional
languages with the mutability tend to
provide a toolbox of techniques for
programming without shared state yeah at
least without shared mutable state
because that's a problem yeah so so it's
that one of the reasons all the main
reasons why f sharp has made it into a
product is because you know multi-core
is becoming more important than
functional languages are useful in that
respect I think that's one of the big
reasons clearly there's there's an
announcement that the functional
programming techniques whether it's you
know whether it's F sharp or some other
language that you know even on the.net
platform we've seen C sharp and Visual
Basic both pick up a few functional
programming person but I think there's a
recognition that those techniques are
going to be an important ingredient in
the
as many core programming era but I think
frappe sharp yes that's one of the big
things it's a language that is built
from the ground up as a functional
language that has the full toolset to
really allow you to replicate programs
that are by and large immutable but have
access to the broader dotnet platform
but I think the beyond that there's
there's other reasons as well why
f-sharp has been sort of moved moved
more into the mainstream of nets which
is that it really is the explorative
idea and the appeal to sort of technical
and algorithmic developers is something
that the dotnet platform hadn't had any
strong language for in the past and so
f-sharp is really trying to sort of
broaden the platform out a bit towards
some of these developers were looking
doing very technical work or algorithmic
work or working in an environment where
they're trying to just explore an
interactive style yeah I'll come back to
this explorative style in a moment but I
want to briefly revisit this
immutability stuff because there is also
a keyword called mutable that allows
data structures to be marked as mutable
because the default is immutable
so it's not it's not a pure functional
language what is the reason why you
introduce this mutable keyword the
compatibility with existing dotnet
frameworks or or because I mean you
could argue that if you do functional
you should do pure functional right yes
so there's often a debate I think
there's been a long-standing debate in
the functional languages community about
you know about purity and about how you
know how far you can go and and what you
should lose by not going all the way
towards purity and saying you really
can't have any shared mutable state
f-sharp is is not a pure functional
language and so it does allow you to do
imperative programming it does allow you
to have shared mutable state and really
the main reason as you said is is the
dotnet platform okay um you know to be
able to access all of the rich
frameworks that are available there
which are really you know they really
are critical to a language beam these
days you know the API that you use are
really a large part
of your programming experience and there
where you you know a language really
gained a lot of its usefulness through
the set of libraries it has access to
the dotnet platform clearly does have
lots of shared mutable state clearly
when you create a you know you create an
array or net you can order values in the
array and these these techniques are
useful programming techniques f-sharp
layers on top of that the ability to do
immutable functional programming on top
of that and another thing that I found
interesting about f-sharp is the fact
that it's strongly typed that's not
necessarily typical for functional
languages although of course there are
others with very sophisticated strongly
typed type systems is is the reason
again the fact that it needs to run
efficiently on the CLR or is there a
more conceptual reason for having a
strongly typed well I mean if sharp
initially inherited from the Okemo
languages and so the ML family of
languages which which all sort of were
strongly statically typed because I've
been friends to be able to give it as
sweet and succinct syntax in the
language and drop really inherited a lot
of the you know it's it's sort of there
are those ideas from the ML family of
languages and from the success that
they've had I think there's also the
idea that you know if you are statically
typed you can you know if you can't
compile down to the CLR and get really
performance runtime but I don't think
I'm we have other languages you know
there's this implementations of Python
and Ruby on net run Python or Ruby which
both are in the dynamic category and I
think they they're able to be quite
effective and quite performant languages
on on the CLR but I think after I've
really sat in this in this particular
spot as being a statically typed
language and gets many of the benefits
from that they're really strong
guarantees from the type system that you
get from being a statically typed
language you mentioned before that
f-sharp is also object oriented so it's
another one of those
attempts although I don't mean to say
that it fails one of those languages
that tries to merge functional and oo so
if you you know primarily advocate
functional style with non mutable state
how does this go together with object
orientation how do these two
philosophies fit together in one
language I think one of the things that
we've seen in practice when in and in
the abstract but also in some of the
other languages like like Scala which
merges these two idea is quite
successfully that they're really they
aren't as they aren't in opposition
they're really sort of in some sense
sort of our saga Newell design ideas
you know functional programming
techniques tend to be about sort of
programming in the small they tend to
really benefit when you're talking about
sort of the kind of things that would
sit inside a method body they do
abstraction and in parallelism and
things but but still the OO techniques
can be used as the packaging constructs
as the way that you've pulled together
components and exposed them is off to
consumers and really scale your
applications up to programming in the
large kind of kind of domains so really
we see in F sharp not not too much
conflict between those ideas they tend
to actually work quite well together in
practice after you know the functional
techniques is the way that you really
write the meat of your application and
then the Oh techniques is the way that
you package and constrain that code and
publish it off to consumers okay is that
though well another one of the
properties you advertise for SRP
scalability is that is that related to
this functional in the small low and a
large kind of approach that you just
talked about yeah I think I think in
part it's it's the idea that you know
once you do get up to a certain level of
scale you know you're your own design
techniques can really kick in in a
language like f-sharp that it does does
have oo and does sit on top of a runtime
environment that um that is designed for
for that sort of oo scale like you know
it's like the CLR is in like Java wood
is um and so you know we showed it we
we've seen in applications developed in
F sharp but
so sort of know just that ultimately
you're going to scale in very very
similar ways to away the like shoe shop
or Java might scale because you're using
the same kinds of techniques when you
get to that scale that you would in
those languages you're using using net
assembly it's your packaging constructed
using classes and oil frameworks for the
way that you break down the components
inside an assembly many of the
techniques are the same
and similarly I guess one other thing I
haven't talked about is the tools F
sharp has sort of strong visual studio
support that's something that we're also
working on to take that a bit further
and so really one of the key parts of
being able scale is the tools and so
since our were built individual studio
we have to have support inside Visual
Studio we are able to give you sort of
the tools that are some natural and
debugging tools the project system for
managing your source code there needed
when you do scale up an application ok
let's talk a little bit about this
explorative buzz word or concept you
mentioned a couple of times and also
read it a couple of times in various F
sharp publications
it's not about explorative programming
and using the language in an explorative
way what does that mean yeah so it's um
it's sort of the idea that one of the
one of the great things about
programming is that it can be used to
distend really solve problems and a lot
of the time when when people are trying
to go out and solve problems using
programming languages it's not that they
sit down and sort of write an
application from scratch they often have
some idea they want to experiment they
have some data that's available to them
and they wanted to sort of open up an
interactive console and then run some
commands build up a little bit of states
and try to figure out the right
algorithm for solving a problem and so
this idea of being able to explore being
able to pull in some data play around
with it write some algorithms write some
codes and it works with that data and
then visualize the results of what
you've accomplished is really what we're
sort of talked about with with
explorative development and in something
that a number of the scripting languages
that have been popular over the recent
years have been used in large part for
these kind of purposes but also in
specific domains there have been lots of
these languages like like MATLAB and
Mathematica have been popular tools for
mathematicians and there's been other
sort of APL are many many other
languages in specific domains that have
been very interesting for going out and
exploring using the sort of magic about
programming that it can be a great tool
for just solving problems and so
whenever we're really trying to take
take net and give it a tool that sort of
strongly types can scale but it's also
available at the sort of explorative end
of the spectrum for just kind of playing
around with code so I guess you then
also have a console and an interpreter
where you can just execute statements
and and function calls and definitions
like interactively as it just said yeah
so there's there's an interactive
there's abstract interactive you can use
to just you can open that up and type in
any f-sharp expressions or defined
f-sharp types or create f-sharp
functions and yeah you can just type
those in just like you would inside
inside an f-sharp application and and
execute them and that's really we also
have some support for that inside Visual
Studio to make that kind of experience
pretty pretty easy to work with um and
so that's that's really in practice what
we're talking about is having an f-sharp
interactive right okay you mentioned Oh
camel before can you talk a little bit
about the other languages from which F
sharp is inspired maybe look at some of
the specific features and then maybe
talk about the where they where it
inherited them from so I mean yeah so
camel is where the sort of core of the
language and certainly the kind of
syntax and feel of the language comes
comes in large parts from from oh camel
I think and the interest obviously
things like things like if the let
keyword being very fundamental and the
language comes from a camel yeah strong
static type inference comes from oh
camel I think if the dotnet integration
comes very strongly from language like C
sharp and Visual Basic so a lot of the
the way in which Joe is done in the
language comes
from c-sharp but with you know with with
ideas from from many other languages
which is successfully sort of looked at
functional plus oo the languages like
Scala which have done that I think
there's a lot of similarities in the
approaches yeah I will talk about that
later
yeah okay great and and then I think
there's also a few features that kind of
come from languages like Haskell so some
of the kind of monadic features in
Haskell and show up in a few ways in
inside f-sharp with ways of doing
sequence comprehensions and doing
asynchronous workflows we talked to
Simon Peyton Jones recently and he you
know talked about being just down the
hallway from you guys and and trying to
make you do the right thing yeah he
works just down the hallway from from
Don Stein who is the original researcher
working on f-sharp and there's an
architect for F sharp so yeah I think I
think they they probably have some some
interesting spirited discussions about
the the various merits of Haskell and F
sharp but but yeah I think there's a lot
of a lot of productive sharing of ideas
and I think Haskell is a big influence
on on a lot of functional programming
languages and then definitely on measure
yeah so of course this raises the
question I mean I have to ask it why
another functional language aren't there
enough or weren't there enough on
the.net platform so what was the reason
to do another language yes I mean I you
know there have been a number of
functional languages but really in some
sense none of them have really I won't
say none of them but so there hasn't
been really this sort of mainstream yet
functional language yet there have been
very strong mainstream procedural
imperative languages or languages a
really functional languages happen sort
of broken cross that barrier to being
really fully in the mainstream though
ideas from functional languages
certainly have they've moved into
industry sharp as I mentioned I guess
they're they're looking at them for for
Java there's you know there's plenty of
ideas that are sort of making their way
through but I think I think gap sharp is
trying to build like a really
functional language for the.net platform
and it really hasn't been hasn't been
won yet that's really been able to sort
of able to a sort of vivid scale that a
mainstream language would need to and is
that because nobody cared to build
something like that or wasn't there
enough marketing or is it maybe that
functional languages generally haven't
made it into the mainstream because
people don't like well the mainstream
people don't like to think in recursion
and stuff yeah I think it's a
combination of everything historically
there probably been a number of reasons
I think you know they've been perception
issues about function languages they've
been real issues about about you know
performance in the past has been an
issue that's much less so now and I
think but I think looking forward
there's just a recognition as we talked
about early on that some of the reasons
why functional programming is an
important technique that's independent
of whether the language is classified I
think as being a functional language
really it's really functional
programming instead of taking each site
I think and and those techniques are
becoming more and more valued as we sort
of move towards many core and
descriptive programming and once one
additional tools for really writing
writing higher-level or kind of code
even inside the method body I think I
think there's sort of an increasing
interest in these functional programming
techniques those ideas move into the
mainstream oh oh and imperative
languages but we're also seeing a need
for sort of practical practical but but
strongly functional languages to live
through on their own on the major
platforms and so I think that's why it's
been a lot of interest in languages like
F sharp and and interest in Scala okay
so one reason why we're talking about
this stuff is because you're doing a
tutorial adopts law so why don't you
tell us a little bit what the tutorial
contents will be I mean obviously I mean
what what should people expect what kind
of knowledge do they have to bring to
the table what do they need to know
before before they can actually
successfully understand what you're
going to talk about sure yes so the
tutorial will be pretty much
introduction and it sort of starts from
starts from no knowledge of f-sharp and
really should have introduces a lot of
the core concepts of f-sharp goes
through some of the things I've talked
about today but we're in a lot more
details and a lot more sort of hands-on
look at all of this in sort of in an
actual seeing what the code looks like
you know seeing what all the language
features are what what kind of things
you can do with the language but in
terms of you know in terms of what kind
of things will sort of assume folks know
in the tutorial I think um I think a
basic knowledge of the sort of dotnet
environment or you know if you have it
if you have a knowledge of the job
environment that's probably enough just
to sort of talk about F sharp but we
won't assume too much that we will cover
ideas in a number of different domains
and then folks who have asked a lot of
knowledge and oh oh and functional and
in other areas we'll probably see see
some things there they're familiar with
as we talk through those and then they
don't need to understand functional
programming as a precondition to the
tutorial oh no definitely not what we'll
cover lots of lots of functional
programming ideas in there but if you
are if you are someone who's got a lot
of familiarity for functional
programming this should be an
interesting tutorial just to excite how
that's applied in sort of a real-world
kind of a language that you used for a
service in real situations right okay
then Luke thank you very much for being
on the show
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dotnet if you want to support us
you can donate to the SU radio team via
the website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and Slashdot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at se - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of SU radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
creative commons 2.5 licence please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pulsate Music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]
you